[
  {
    "question": "How does active use of gadgets affect people?",
    "answer": "Digital fatigue"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does globalization affect world politics?",
    "answer": "Internationalization"
  },
  {
    "question": "How does sociology divide society by different statuses?",
    "answer": "Social structure"
  },
  {
    "question": "How is malaria transmitted?",
    "answer": "By mosquito bite"
  },
  {
    "question": "How many years does a bachelor's degree take?",
    "answer": "Four"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what language was the Old Testament written?",
    "answer": "Hebrew"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what year did apartheid end in South Africa?",
    "answer": "1994"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what year did the Thirty Years' War begin?",
    "answer": "1618"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what year was the Magna Carta signed?",
    "answer": "Monetary policy"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what year was the Treaty of Versailles signed?",
    "answer": "1919"
  },
  {
    "question": "In what year was the first women's college founded?",
    "answer": "1837"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which country is Yom Kippur a public holiday?",
    "answer": "Israel"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which country is the headquarters of the World Bank located?",
    "answer": "USA"
  },
  {
    "question": "In which direction is globalization developing?",
    "answer": "Integration"
  },
  {
    "question": "Name a genetic blood disorder.",
    "answer": "Hemophilia"
  },
  {
    "question": "Social policy in a democratic society?",
    "answer": "Transparency and participation"
  },
  {
    "question": "The critical period of development is called...",
    "answer": "Critical age"
  },
  {
    "question": "The study of criminal behavior is called",
    "answer": "Criminology"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are Chinese characters called?",
    "answer": "Hanzi"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are devices called that perform work for humans?",
    "answer": "Robots"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the goods called that are used for further production?",
    "answer": "Intermediate goods"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the main gods of Hinduism called?",
    "answer": "Trimurti"
  },
  {
    "question": "What are the types of social mobility?",
    "answer": "Horizontal and vertical"
  },
  {
    "question": "What concept describes equal opportunities for everyone?",
    "answer": "Inclusion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What concept did Merton introduce to explain deviant behavior?",
    "answer": "Anomie"
  },
  {
    "question": "What describes the distribution of power resources in society?",
    "answer": "Political sociology"
  },
  {
    "question": "What devices are used for home security?",
    "answer": "Surveillance systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "What do non-governmental funds do?",
    "answer": "Charity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does 'ethical pluralism' mean?",
    "answer": "Diversity of values"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does 'thing-in-itself' mean according to Kant?",
    "answer": "unthinkable object"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does 'value' represent?",
    "answer": "Worth"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does a pulse oximeter do?",
    "answer": "Measures saturation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does a spirometer measure?",
    "answer": "Lung volume"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does biological anthropology study?",
    "answer": "Human evolution"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does blockchain technology do?",
    "answer": "Recording transactions"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does clinical psychology study?",
    "answer": "Mental disorders"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does cybernetics study?",
    "answer": "Control of systems"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does ecofeminism study?",
    "answer": "The connection between ecology and feminism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does economic sociology study?",
    "answer": "The interaction between economy and society"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does ethnomethodology study?",
    "answer": "Everyday interactions"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does gender psychology study?",
    "answer": "Gender differences"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does globalization lead to?",
    "answer": "Cultural blending"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does hermeneutics deal with?",
    "answer": "interpretation of texts"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does phenomenology study?",
    "answer": "Phenomena"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the CIS do?",
    "answer": "Cooperation of countries"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the concept of 'deontology' mean?",
    "answer": "moral duties"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the ethical concept of 'duty' reflect?",
    "answer": "Moral obligations"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the science of 'Welfare Economics' study?",
    "answer": "Resource allocation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the term \"interculturalism\" mean?",
    "answer": "Dialogue of cultures"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the term 'anamnesis' mean?",
    "answer": "Recollection"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the term 'codification' mean?",
    "answer": "creation of a code"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the term 'ontology' mean?",
    "answer": "The study of being"
  },
  {
    "question": "What does the term 'recession' mean?",
    "answer": "Economic downturn"
  },
  {
    "question": "What economic process supports globalization?",
    "answer": "Liberalization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What factor influences the global market?",
    "answer": "Innovation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What form do international treaties take?",
    "answer": "written"
  },
  {
    "question": "What forms the basis of cognitive schemas?",
    "answer": "Experience"
  },
  {
    "question": "What helps create digital artificial content?",
    "answer": "Graphic editors"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is 'anaphylactic shock'?",
    "answer": "Allergic reaction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a digital footprint?",
    "answer": "Internet activity"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a legal norm?",
    "answer": "Mandatory rule"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a priority area in the economy?",
    "answer": "Key development area"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is a teletype in the media business?",
    "answer": "A text transmission device"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an 'aporia'?",
    "answer": "Logical paradox"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an element of material culture?",
    "answer": "Architecture"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is an object of cultural rights?",
    "answer": "Heritage"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is cultural relativism?",
    "answer": "The relativity of cultural norms"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is ethical subjectivism?",
    "answer": "Personal opinion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is ethnomethodology?",
    "answer": "Study of everyday actions"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is important when studying artifacts?",
    "answer": "Context"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is marginal cost?",
    "answer": "Additional costs"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is reaction formation?",
    "answer": "Opposite expression"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is sociometry?",
    "answer": "A method of analysis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is subjective value?",
    "answer": "Value to the individual"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the disease called that is caused by the destruction of cartilage?",
    "answer": "Osteoarthritis"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the doctrine called that asserts human actions are predetermined?",
    "answer": "Determinism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the educational institution for adults called?",
    "answer": "Institute"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the first court session called?",
    "answer": "preliminary"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the form of education called where study is combined with work?",
    "answer": "Dual system"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the form of government called where the head of state primarily performs ceremonial duties?",
    "answer": "Constitutional monarchy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the form of government with local self-government called?",
    "answer": "Federation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the group of people called that considers a case in court?",
    "answer": "Jury"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the holy site located in Mecca?",
    "answer": "Kaaba"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main purpose of lobbying?",
    "answer": "Influencing decisions"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the main purpose of propaganda?",
    "answer": "Influence opinion"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of a law enforcement officer?",
    "answer": "Police officer"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the ancient Greek harvest festival?",
    "answer": "Thesmophoria"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the doctrine that evaluates morality in terms of consequences?",
    "answer": "Consequentialism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the famous African style of masks?",
    "answer": "Punu masks"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the international court?",
    "answer": "International Court of Justice"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the international organization that fights against torture?",
    "answer": "Amnesty International"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the international relations theory that focuses on power interests?",
    "answer": "Realism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the philosophical doctrine that centers around the idea of constant change?",
    "answer": "Dialectics"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the program that supports citizens' income during crisis moments in life?",
    "answer": "Social insurance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the thyroid gland disease characterized by increased functional activity?",
    "answer": "Hyperthyroidism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the name of the work by philosopher Francis Bacon related to the scientific revolution?",
    "answer": "Novum Organum"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the philosophy called that emphasizes the importance of consequences?",
    "answer": "Consequentialism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the political theory that advocates for minimal government intervention in the economy called?",
    "answer": "Libertarianism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the primary significance of rituals in anthropology?",
    "answer": "Social functions"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the procedure of listening to the heart called?",
    "answer": "Auscultation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of a person's adaptation to changing conditions called?",
    "answer": "Adaptation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of eliminating harmful substances called?",
    "answer": "Detoxification"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of learning gender roles called?",
    "answer": "Gender socialization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of passing culture through generations called?",
    "answer": "Cultural tradition"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of protecting copyright called?",
    "answer": "Copyright registration"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of protecting rights called?",
    "answer": "Judicial proceedings"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of reliving a traumatic event called?",
    "answer": "Flashback"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the process of social integration of different countries called?",
    "answer": "Social globalization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the psychological distress due to a mismatch of gender called?",
    "answer": "Gender dysphoria"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the psychological state of self-love called?",
    "answer": "Narcissism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the right to protection from arbitrary interference in personal life called?",
    "answer": "Privacy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the science of blood called?",
    "answer": "Hematology"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the science of medicinal plants called?",
    "answer": "Pharmacognosy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the scientific study of social change and development called?",
    "answer": "Social theory"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the subject of a contract?",
    "answer": "Terms of the agreement"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the technique of gesture control called?",
    "answer": "Gesture Control"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term for spiritual self-improvement in Taoism?",
    "answer": "Dao"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term for the difference between a government's income and expenses?",
    "answer": "Budget deficit"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the term for the transmission of cultural traditions from generation to generation?",
    "answer": "Socialization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is the transition from mortal life to the afterlife called in Christianity?",
    "answer": "Dormition"
  },
  {
    "question": "What is utilitarianism?",
    "answer": "ethics of utility"
  },
  {
    "question": "What laws govern relations at the international level?",
    "answer": "International law"
  },
  {
    "question": "What limits 'scarcity'?",
    "answer": "Available resources"
  },
  {
    "question": "What movement opposes corporate control and inequality?",
    "answer": "Anti-consumerism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What movement opposes globalization?",
    "answer": "Anti-globalization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What movement was the Petrograd Soviet?",
    "answer": "Soviet"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon contributes to global mobility?",
    "answer": "Migration"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon describes a sharp decline in population?",
    "answer": "Depopulation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What phenomenon includes the norms of society?",
    "answer": "Social control"
  },
  {
    "question": "What philosophical term means 'existence'?",
    "answer": "Being"
  },
  {
    "question": "What principle did Zeno of Citium propose?",
    "answer": "Apathy"
  },
  {
    "question": "What protects children's rights?",
    "answer": "Convention"
  },
  {
    "question": "What right allows participation in elections?",
    "answer": "Suffrage"
  },
  {
    "question": "What right does a citizen's passport protect?",
    "answer": "Right to citizenship"
  },
  {
    "question": "What right guarantees participation in public life?",
    "answer": "Right to assembly"
  },
  {
    "question": "What role do megacities play?",
    "answer": "Global hubs"
  },
  {
    "question": "What script is used in Sikhism?",
    "answer": "Gurmukhi"
  },
  {
    "question": "What style is characteristic of the Renaissance era?",
    "answer": "Renaissance"
  },
  {
    "question": "What substance in blood serum helps fight infections?",
    "answer": "Antibodies"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology converts solar energy into electricity?",
    "answer": "Photovoltaics"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology converts sound into text?",
    "answer": "Speech recognition"
  },
  {
    "question": "What technology powers cryptocurrencies?",
    "answer": "Blockchain"
  },
  {
    "question": "What term describes the corrupt practice of using one's official position?",
    "answer": "Nepotism"
  },
  {
    "question": "What term describes the development of technologies in education?",
    "answer": "EdTech"
  },
  {
    "question": "What term describes the phenomenon of internet addiction?",
    "answer": "Internet addiction"
  },
  {
    "question": "What term describes the process of mixing cultures?",
    "answer": "Interculturation"
  },
  {
    "question": "What term is often used in the context of globalization?",
    "answer": "Glocalization"
  },
  {
    "question": "What term refers to the systematic planning of the educational process?",
    "answer": "Curriculum"
  },
  {
    "question": "What trend is characteristic of the global economy?",
    "answer": "Increasing interdependence"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of course is typically short and focused on specific skills?",
    "answer": "Mini-course"
  },
  {
    "question": "What type of educational activity involves writing a dissertation?",
    "answer": "Research work"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the name of the ancient Indian empire?",
    "answer": "Maurya"
  },
  {
    "question": "What was the war between England and France in the 14th century called?",
    "answer": "Hundred Years' War"
  },
  {
    "question": "When did the migrant rights movement first emerge?",
    "answer": "19th century"
  },
  {
    "question": "When was the Byzantine Empire founded?",
    "answer": "395"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where are global human rights issues discussed?",
    "answer": "United Nations Human Rights Council"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where are laws enacted in a federal system?",
    "answer": "Federal Assembly"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where are pension fund assets invested?",
    "answer": "Securities"
  },
  {
    "question": "Where did the 'Green Morning' movement take place?",
    "answer": "In Kenya"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which anthropological concept explains the vertical structure of society?",
    "answer": "Social stratification"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which anthropologist developed the method of ethnography?",
    "answer": "Bronisław Malinowski"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which architect designed the Sagrada Familia?",
    "answer": "Gaudi"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which article of the European Convention on Human Rights protects the right to a fair trial?",
    "answer": "Article 6"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which article of the Universal Declaration of Human Rights protects the right to privacy?",
    "answer": "Article 12"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which church reformation began in the 16th century?",
    "answer": "Protestant"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which city is considered the financial center of the world?",
    "answer": "New York"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which country is not a signatory of the European Convention on Human Rights?",
    "answer": "Belarus"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which decade is considered the beginning of the feminist movement in Russia?",
    "answer": "1910s"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which doctrine claims that the Universe possesses intelligence?",
    "answer": "Pantheism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which dynasty ruled China from the late 14th to the early 17th century?",
    "answer": "Ming"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which dynasty ruled England in the 12th-13th centuries?",
    "answer": "Plantagenets"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which feminist text criticized female passivity?",
    "answer": "The Women's Gospel"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which feminist theorist is known for her work on patriarchy?",
    "answer": "Silvia Federici"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which industries dominate the world?",
    "answer": "technological"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which law regulates social security in Russia?",
    "answer": "Federal Law No. 255-FZ"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which media format does not exist?",
    "answer": "Googlecasts"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which movement campaigned against nuclear weapons?",
    "answer": "Campaign for Nuclear Disarmament"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which organizations are involved in social support?",
    "answer": "Charitable foundations"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which part of the tooth is responsible for its sensitivity?",
    "answer": "Dentin"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which philosopher claimed that 'existence precedes essence'?",
    "answer": "Sartre"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which philosophical direction claims that the world is completely knowable?",
    "answer": "Rationalism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which principle respects cultural diversity and intercultural dialogue?",
    "answer": "Multiculturalism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which program helps to increase employment?",
    "answer": "Employment Center"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which program provides free medication for retirees?",
    "answer": "FL"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which region has been most affected by globalization?",
    "answer": "Africa"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which region is the most integrated into the process of globalization?",
    "answer": "The West"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which right protects against violence?",
    "answer": "Personal"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which right protects the freedom of movement?",
    "answer": "Right to movement"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which ruler implemented major reforms in Japan in 1868?",
    "answer": "Emperor Meiji"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which school of philosophy used paradoxes?",
    "answer": "Eleatics"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which science studies tissues?",
    "answer": "Histology"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which style did Van Gogh popularize?",
    "answer": "Post-Impressionism"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which system supports the employment level?",
    "answer": "Social policy"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which theory analyzes the intersection of different forms of oppression?",
    "answer": "Intersectionality"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which theory examines the influence of gender on language?",
    "answer": "Feminist linguistics"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which theory explains inequality in society?",
    "answer": "Conflict"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which theory studies the performativity of gender?",
    "answer": "Judith Butler's Theory"
  },
  {
    "question": "Which transportation system facilitated global trade?",
    "answer": "Container shipping"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who can apply to the European Court of Human Rights?",
    "answer": "Any citizen"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who conducted the famous survey in Chicago?",
    "answer": "E. W. Burgess"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who creates content for newspapers?",
    "answer": "Journalists"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who determines economic policy?",
    "answer": "Government"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who developed structuralism in sociology?",
    "answer": "Claude Lévi-Strauss"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who developed the concept of 'will to power'?",
    "answer": "Friedrich Nietzsche"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who developed the concept of behavioral economics?",
    "answer": "Daniel Kahneman"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who developed the concept of cultural universals?",
    "answer": "George Murdock"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who developed the theory of justice as fairness?",
    "answer": "John Rawls"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who founded Stoicism?",
    "answer": "Zeno"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who founded the Bahá'í Faith?",
    "answer": "Bahá'u'lláh"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who founded the neoclassical economic theory?",
    "answer": "Alfred Marshall"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who gives the mandate to govern the country in elections?",
    "answer": "Citizens"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who introduced the concept of 'globalization' in cultural studies?",
    "answer": "Roland Robertson"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who introduced the term 'Postmodern'?",
    "answer": "Jean-François Lyotard"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who introduced the term 'anomie'?",
    "answer": "Durkheim"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who introduced the term 'charisma'?",
    "answer": "Max Weber"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who introduced the term 'existentialism'?",
    "answer": "Jean-Paul Sartre"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who introduced the term 'profanation'?",
    "answer": "Henri Lefebvre"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is considered one of the founders of masculinity studies?",
    "answer": "R.W. Connell"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is considered the father of anthropology?",
    "answer": "Tylor"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is considered the founder of feminism?",
    "answer": "Simone de Beauvoir"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is considered the founder of structural functionalism?",
    "answer": "Talcott Parsons"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is known for their work in queer theory?",
    "answer": "Judith Butler"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is one of the principal deities in Hinduism?",
    "answer": "Brahma"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the author of 'Utilitarianism'?",
    "answer": "Mill"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the author of the book 'Anthropology Treatise'?",
    "answer": "Claude Lévi-Strauss"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the author of the book 'Correspondence School'?",
    "answer": "Ushinsky"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the author of the book 'Suicide'?",
    "answer": "Émile Durkheim"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the author of the concept of justice as fairness?",
    "answer": "John Rawls"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the author of the concept of positive thinking?",
    "answer": "Martin Seligman"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the author of the work 'Leviathan'?",
    "answer": "Thomas Hobbes"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the founder of Taoism?",
    "answer": "Laozi"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who is the founder of symbolic interactionism?",
    "answer": "Herbert Blumer"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who issues rulings?",
    "answer": "The court"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who led the Salt March?",
    "answer": "Mahatma Gandhi"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who proposed the social learning theory?",
    "answer": "Bandura"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who ruled France after Napoleon?",
    "answer": "Louis XVIII"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who said: 'Man is the measure of all things'?",
    "answer": "Protagoras"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who studied the influence of culture on personality?",
    "answer": "Margaret Mead"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was one of the leaders of the anti-colonial movements in Africa?",
    "answer": "Kwame Nkrumah"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the first Prime Minister of the United Kingdom?",
    "answer": "Walpole"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who was the leader of the migrant rights movement in the USA?",
    "answer": "Cesar Chavez"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who wrote 'Ethics' in the 17th century?",
    "answer": "Spinoza"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who wrote 'The Arguments of Anthropology'?",
    "answer": "Jack Goody"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who wrote 'The Second Sex'?",
    "answer": "Simone de Beauvoir"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who wrote the 'Declaration of the Rights of Man and of the Citizen'?",
    "answer": "Mirabeau"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who wrote the book 'Gender Trouble'?",
    "answer": "Judith Butler"
  },
  {
    "question": "Who wrote the work 'The Chrysanthemum and the Sword'?",
    "answer": "Ruth Benedict"
  }
]